现在我们关注的最后几个部分
now the last few sections we focused on
模式匹配
pattern matching
特别是字符串和映射
specifically with strings and maps
因为模式匹配是一个
because pattern matching is a
不同的编程思维方式
different way of thinking about programming
这需要一些练习
and it takes a bit of practice
你会到处使用模式匹配
and you'll use pattern matching all over the place
即使是某种东西的灵丹妙药
an elixir even for something
像阅读文件一样简单和熟悉
as straightforward and familiar as reading a file
我在想也许你有一个文件
I'm thinking maybe you have a file in mind
事实上
as a matter of fact
我创建了一个顶级页面目录，其中包含 about
I've created a top level pages directory with an about
html文件在里面
html file in it
现在你可以制作自己的文件了
now you can make your own file
或者您可以在代码包中找到此文件
or you can find this file in the code bundle
我们希望在收到请求时提供此文件
and we want to serve this file when we get a request
斜线约
for slash about
所以我们手头已经有一个请求奶嘴了
so we already have a request teat up over in hand
例如，请求是斜线
ex the request is get slash about
我们准备了一个路由函数
and we've prepared a route function that
匹配请求
matches the request
因为这里没有什么新东西要学
since there's nothing new to learn here
它看起来像这样
it just looks like this
我们将在路径斜杠上进行模式匹配
we're going to pattern match on the path slash about
然后显然我们要填写
and then obviously we want to fill in
响应体
the response body
与文件的内容
with the contents of the file
现在，如果我们运行它，它应该可以工作
for now though if we run it it should work
是的，我们刚回来
yep we just get back
文件内容so
contents of file so
我们需要将文件作为这些内容提供
we need to serve the file as those contents
所以让我们跳吧
so let's hop
转到 ix 会话以查看如何读取文件
over to an ix session to see how to read a file
我将使用 h
I'm going to use the h
辅助函数
helper function
然后
and then the
文件模块包含一堆函数
file module contains a bunch of functions for
处理文件
working with files
我们想读取一个文件，所以不足为奇
we want to read a file so no surprise
该函数称为读取
the function is called a read
它说它返回这个
and it says that it returns this
如果读取文件成功或这件事
if reading the file was successful or this thing
如果读取文件是一个错误
if reading the file was an error
那么花括号中的这些东西是什么
so what are these things in curly braces
好吧，这就是所谓的元组
well it's something called a tuple
元组只是一个有序的
and a tuple is just an ordered
花括号中的值集合
collection of values in curly braces
最常见的你会看到
most commonly you'll see like
这些中的两到四个值
two to four values in these
所以在成功的情况下
so in the case of success
元组的第一个元素
the first element of the tuple
在这种情况下是一个原子没关系
is an atom in this case it's okay
然后第二个元素是二进制
and then the second element is a binary
记住字符串是长生不老药中的二进制文件，所以
remember strings are binaries in elixir so
这将是文件中的内容
this is going to be the contents in the file
如果有错误
and if there's an error
那么第一个元素是原子错误
then the first element is the atom error
然后我们将得到一个原因变量
and then we're going to get a reason variable
这必然会产生一些结果
and that'll be bound to some result
如果我们往下看，我们会看到典型的错误
and if we look down below we see the typical error
原因类似于原子
reasons would be something like the atom
e 和 to 表示文件不存在
e and to which indicates that the file does not exist
许多内置的长生不老药功能使用
many built in elixir functions use
这个返回元组的成语
this idiom that returns a tuple
那么我们如何检查读取文件是否成功
so how do we check that reading a file was successful
如果是这样，提取其内容
and if so extract its contents
你猜对了
well you guessed it
通过在返回元组上使用模式匹配
by using pattern matching on the return tuple
我们只是要清理这个
we're just going to clean this up
所以我们回到顶部
so we go back up to the top
所以我们可以使用文件点读取和
so we can use file dot read and
因为我在顶级调查目录中启动了 ix
because I started ix in the top level survey directory
那么我们关于文件的相对路径将是
then the relative path to our about file is going to be
页面
pages
关于 html，我们知道这将返回一个元组
about html and we know that's going to return a tuple
我们希望这会成功
and we expect this to succeed
所以我们可以将它与原子匹配
so we can match it against the atom
好的，然后内容将被绑定
okay and then the contents will get bound
到那个文件的内容
to the contents of that file
如果我们看内容，果然是匹配的
and sure enough it's a match if we look at contents
好吧，我们已经有了文件的内容
well we've had the contents of our file
好吧，让我们看看该文件不存在
well let's see that the file doesn't exist
例如我们看起来很陌生关于我们的文件
for example we look foreign about us file
是的，如果我们尝试
yeah if we try that
然后比赛失败
then the match fails
因为它实际上是返回一个元组
because it's actually returning a tuple
错误作为第一个元素，然后这个
with error as the first element and then this
文件不存在原子作为第二个元素
file not exist atom as the second element
那么我们要如何处理失败的情况
so how do we want to handle the case where it fails
好吧，我们可以为此写一场比赛
well we can write a match for that
是的，我们将在这里更改比赛
yeah we'll just change the match here
这将匹配一个错误
this is going to match an error
然后我们要捕获实际的错误
and then we want to capture the actual error in
原因变量
a reason variable
这是一场比赛，如果我们看看原因
and that's a match and if we look at reason
嗯，就是那个原子
well it's that atom
告诉我们该文件不存在
that tells us that the file doesn't exist
所以现在回到我们的路线功能
so now back in our route function
我们首先
we first
需要读取文件，我们知道该怎么做
need to read the file and we know how to do that
但相对于处理程序的目录
but relative to the directory of the handler
ex 文件是两个目录，所以我们将使用
ex file it's two directories up so we're going to use
就这样斜线
slash just like that
然后我们可以使用
and then we can use a
case 表达式来处理
case expression to handle the
成功与失败场景
success and failure scenario
所以我们说case，然后do，end
so we say case and then do and end
然后在箱子里面
and then inside of the case
我们可以匹配文件的结果
we can match the result of the file
针对多种模式的芦苇表达
reed expression against multiple patterns
所以第一个匹配的模式将是
so the first pattern will match will be
好的，然后内容，我们用一个小箭头
okay and then content and we use a little arrow
在那种特殊情况下，我们想要采取
in that particular case we want to take the
co 和 v 映射并将状态更新为 200
co and v map and update the status to be a 200
和响应体
and the response body
无论内容是什么
is going to be whatever that content is
然后在有错误的情况下
then in the case that there's an error
我们会有元组错误
we'll have the tuple error
然后我们将捕获原因
and then we'll capture the reason
就像我们在 ix
just like we did in ix
在这种情况下，我们要返回
in this case we want to return
对话地图有
a conversation map that has
状态为 500
a status of 500
和响应体
and the response body
我们只想说
we're just going to say
归档空气，然后将插入原因
file air and then will interpolate the reason
所以我们有一个匹配所有错误的模式
so we have a pattern that matches all errors
但是假设我们要返回一个四
but let's say we want to return a four
或四个有特定错误
or four with a specific error
如果找不到文件
if the file isn't found
好吧，我们可以在最后一个分支之上添加那个分支
well we can add that branch above this final branch
所以模式看起来像错误
so the pattern's going to look like error
但这将是一个特定的错误
but it's going to be a specific error
就是那个 e 和 to amp t atom
it's that e and to amp t atom
在那里面
in that
如果我们要打开一张看起来像这样的地图
case we were going to turn a map that looks like this
状态将是四或四
the status is going to be a four or four
身体会说
and the body is just going to say
文件未找到
file not found
所以请记住这里的顺序很重要
so just remember that the order here matters
第一个匹配的模式将获胜并且
the first pattern that matches is going to win and
这就是为什么我们放置
that's why we placed
这个模式在这个模式之上，因为这是一个更
this pattern above this pattern because this is a more
通用形式它只会捕捉任何原因
generic form it's just going to capture any reason
在那个原因变量
in that reason variable
这是一个特定的文字匹配
where this is a specific literal match
在那个亚当上，而且经常
on that adam e and often
以及任何模式匹配的结果
and the result of whichever pattern matches
成为的结果
becomes the result of the
整体案例表达
overall case expression
所以我们在这里不需要这条线
so we don't need this line down here
因为我们的案例将返回更新后的地图
because our case is going to return the updated map
现在如果我们运行它
now if we run it
我们看到我们得到的报价是
we see we've got the quote as the
该响应的正文
body of that response
现在如果我们把它改成关于我们然后运行它
now if we change it to about us and then run it
好吧，我们应该看到那里找不到文件
well we should see the file not found there
是的，我们得到了四个或四个
yep we get a four or four
所以现在让我们把它改回大约
so now let's change it back to about
让我们从命令行运行它
and let's run it from the command line
好的，我已经改了
alright I've got it changed
然后在命令行
and then at the command line
我在调查目录的顶层
I'm at the top level of survey directory
所以我运行长生不老药
so I run elixir
lib调查处理程序前
lib survey handler ex
哦，它说找不到文件
ooh and it says file not found
那是因为我们在顶层运行
and that's because we're running at the top level
调查目录
survey directory
在我们的代码中，我们试图找到关于页面
and in our code we're trying to find the about page
相对于这个目录
relative to this directory
现在斜线页面
slash pages now
这适用于崇高，因为当前目录是
this works in sublime because the current directory is
lib斜线调查
lib slash survey
所以我们需要得到about的绝对路径
so we need to get the absolute path to the about
html文件，所以可以找到
html file so it can be found
无论在哪个目录中
regardless of which directory were in
应用程序运行时
when the app is run
这是获取绝对路径的方法
here's how to get the absolute path
我将使用
and I'm going to use
一分钟的临时变量
temporary variables for a minute
但我们会用管道清理它
but we'll clean this up with a pipeline
稍晚一些
a little bit later
所以假设我们有一个页面路径变量
so let's say we have a pages path variable
然后
and then the
elixir 中的路径模块有一大堆功能
path module in elixir has a whole bunch of functions
用于处理路径
for dealing with paths
其中一项功能是展开
one of those functions is expand
而我们要做的就是拓展这条路
and what we want to do is expand this path
相对于所在目录的页面
pages relative to the directory in which
该文件已定义
this file is defined
我们可以通过使用下划线来得到它
and we can get that by using underscore
下划线 下划线
underscore underscore
所以这将返回的绝对路径
so this returns the absolute path of the
当前文件的目录
directory of the current file
其中处理程序
wherein handler
ex 所以这将是通往 lib 的绝对路径
ex so that's going to be the absolute path down to lib
服务然后路径扩展将扩展此路径
serve and then path expand is going to expand this path
相对于第二条路径
relative to this 2nd path
所以页面路径将是绝对路径
so pages path is going to be the absolute path
到这个页面目录
down to this pages directory
现在这给了我们目录
now that gives us the directory
但我们还需要加入实际文件
but we also need to join on the actual file
所以这样做
so to do that
我们将有一个变量文件，它将是路径
we'll have a variable file and it's going to be path
有一个连接功能，它需要我们的页面路径
there's a join function and it takes in our pages path
然后我们想加入关于
and then we want to join on about
html，这将确保
html and that'll make sure to
使用适当的文件分隔符
use a proper file separator
所以现在我们知道了这些函数是如何工作的
so now that we know how these functions work
以及他们采取的论据
and the arguments they take
让我们删除临时变量和
let's remove the temporary variables and
改用管道
use a pipeline instead
所以最终我们想要一个文件
so ultimately we want a file
我们可以采取扩展路径
we can take the expanded path
然后通过管道将其输入
and then pipe it into
路径联合，这意味着这条路径将是
path joint which means this path is going to be
第一个传入的参数
the first argument that's piped in
所以我们可以摆脱它
so we can get rid of that
然后在文件点读取
and then down in file dot read
而我们只是传递那个文件
while we just pass it that file
所以让我们以崇高的方式运行它并且它可以工作
so let's run it in sublime and it works
如果我们从命令行运行它
and if we run it from the command line
它也可以
it works as well
现在我们要在这里做出设计决定
now we have a design decision to make here
键的表达式只是有条件地运行的一种方式
a key's expression is just a way to conditionally run
基于模式匹配的代码
code based on pattern matches
我们知道有条件地运行代码的另一种方式
and we know a different way to run code conditionally
多子句函数
multi clause functions
所以我要复制我们的版本
so I'm going to copy the version of our
使用 case 的路由函数
route function that uses case
我要评论它
and I'm going to comment it out
只是这样我们在这里完成后可以比较它
just so we can compare it when we're done here
然后粘贴到上面
and then paste it in up above
然后我将注释掉这个 case 表达式
and then I'm going to comment out this case expression
所以让我们继续我们的管道并表达
so let's continue on with our pipeline and express
我们在这里想要什么
what we want here
此时我们有一个加入的绝对路径
at this point we have a joined absolute path
我们想通过管道将其导入文件读取
we want to pipe that into file read
我们知道这将返回一个元组
and we know that's going to return a tuple
那么我们可以转过身来管道那个元组
so then we can turn around and pipe that tuple
进入一个我们还没有写的新函数
into a new function we haven't written yet
我将其称为句柄文件
I'm going to call it handle file
它将把元组作为第一个参数
it's going to take the tuple as the first argument
而且我们还需要传入对话地图
and we also need to pass in the conversation map
所以这将是第二个论点
so that's going to be the second argument
这将返回一个更新的对话地图
and that's going to return an updated conversation map
所以我们可以平等地摆脱这个文件
so we can get rid of this file equal
那将是
and that's going to be the
整个函数体就在那里
entire function body right there
然后我们只需要定义这个
and then we just need to define this
处理文件功能
handle file function
只是为了让它多一点空间
and just to make it a little bit more space
让我们继续并摆脱这个
let's just go ahead and get rid of this
因为我们在下面的函数中得到了它
because we've got it in the function down below
所以看起来像这个句柄文件
so it looks like this handle file
我们知道这需要倾倒
we know it takes a topple
我们可以在上面进行模式匹配
and we can pattern match on that
所以如果没关系和内容
so if it's okay and content
记住还有第二个论点
remember there's a second argument
就是这里的对话
it's the conversation that got passed in right here
所以
so
第一个参数得到管道，第二个参数
the first argument gets piped and the second argument
我们只是传递 co no 那样
we just pass in co no like that
所以如果那个模式匹配
so if that pattern matches
那么我们要做的是返回
then what we want to do is return
这张更新的地图
this updated map
所以我想你知道这是怎么回事
so I think you see where this is going
我们可以定义另一个句柄文件函数子句
we can define another handle file function clause
我们要在这里匹配的模式就是这个
and the pattern we want to match here is this one
然后它需要 co 和 v
and then it takes co and v
然后在那种情况下，我们将返回
and then in that case we were going to return
这张更新的地图
this updated map
还有一次我们得到了句柄文件
and one more time we've got handle file
把这个模式带到这里
that takes this pattern down here
地图
the map
它应该返回
and it should return
这张更新的地图
this updated map
所以我们有三个
so we have three
使用模式匹配的函数子句
function clauses that use pattern matching
并记住一个函数是否有多个子句
and remember if a function has multiple clauses
而长生不老药会尝试
while elixir will try
每个子句，直到找到匹配的子句
each clause until it finds one that matches
并运行第一个匹配的函数子句
and the first function clause that matches is run
所以如果我们把它保存起来
so if we save that away
试一试
and give it a go
虽然我们仍然得到我们的报价作为内容
while we still get our quote as the content of that
正在提供的文件
file that's being served
所以我们得到完全相同的输出
so we get the exact same output
就像我们在使用 case 表达式时所做的那样
as we did when we use the case expression
那么哪种方式更好
so which way is better
使用 case 或 multi 子句函数
using case or multi clause functions
就像我之前提到的
well as I mentioned earlier
这真的是一个设计决定
it's really a design decision and
没有正确或错误的答案
there's no right or wrong answer
你做出的选择
the choice you make
将根据情况和您的
will vary depending on the situation and your
个人喜好
personal preference
在这种情况下，情况很简单，可以阅读
in this situation the case is simple enough to read
它有三个分支和
it has three branches and
与每个分支关联的一行
one line associated with each branch
现在如果它有更多的分支或
now if it had more branches or
每个分支的多行表达式
multiline expressions for each of those branches
然后可读性开始受到影响
then the readability starts to suffer
我会改用多子句函数
and I'd use multi clause functions instead
唯一的缺点
the only downside
多子句功能是你必须定义
to multi clause functions is that you have to define
每个分支的单独功能
separate functions for each branch
但我真的很喜欢分开的声明感
but I really like the declarative feel of separate
小功能
small functions
具有模式匹配的参数
with arguments that are pattern matched
只是感觉更多
it just feels more
符合灵丹妙药的做事方式
congruent with the elixir way of doing things
话虽如此，我们并不完全一致
that being said we're not totally consistent
所以尝试这两种方法来发展你自己的喜好
so try both approaches to develop your own preferences
鉴于情况
given the situation
不要害怕改变主意
and don't be afraid to change your mind
并更改您的代码
and change your code